Guide to the McMullen Family Papers, 1783-1969 and undated, bulk 1880-1945
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McMullen Family papers 1783-1969 and undated bulk 1880-1945
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McMullen family
13.4 linear feet Extent: 10,053 Items
Family of Irish origin living in Pennsylvania, Baltimore, and Washington, D.C. Family and business correspondence and invention papers of an Irish Catholic family living in Pennsylvania, Baltimore, Md., and Washington, D.C., whose members engaged in promoting inventions. The papers center on John Francis McMullen (1830-1900), and his wife, Lavelette (Johnson) McMullen. Includes letters from relatives in Ireland, from Virginia cousins and friends, from nuns of the Order of the Visitation of Holy Mary, from business acquaintances, from friends traveling in the U.S. and Europe, and from the novelist Mary Johnston; and papers relating to the settlement of a disputed legacy left to Mary McMullen by Miss Jane Agnes Riggs, the last of the children of George Washington Riggs, Washington banker. Also includes manuscripts of the Confederate poet, John Banister Tabb, writings of Dysart and Mary McMullen, letters and poems of William Hand Browne, editor, author, and librarian, and correspondence of Mary McMullen which gives glimpses of the Riggs family.
RL.00882
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The McMullen Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1966 and 1975.
Collection Overview
Family and business correspondence and invention papers of the McMullen family, spanning the years 1783-1969, with the majority of the material dating from about 1880-1945. Arranged in the following series: Correspondence, Legal Papers, Pictures, Financial Papers, Invention Papers, Miscellaneous, and Volumes.
The papers of John McMullen (1791-1870), inventor, consist of correspondence concerning family matters in Ireland; McMullen's efforts to assist relatives in gaining passage to the United States, the operation of his farm in Sinking Valley in Pennsylvania; a trip to England, 1850-1851, to sell his inventions; the invention of machines to knit stockings and fish nets; patents; the receipt of the Exhibitor's Medal for a machine shown at the Exhibition of the Works of All Nations at the Crystal Palace, London, England, in 1853 including a letter from President Millard Fillmore notifying him of the award; and an exhibition of a knitting machine at the New York Crystal Palace at the Exhibition of the Industry of All Nations in 1854.
The papers of John Francis McMullen (1830-1900), son of John McMullen, and of his wife, Lavalette (Johnston) McMullen (d. 1941), daughter of John Warfield Johnston, senator from Virginia, include correspondence while John Francis McMullen attended St. Mary's College, Baltimore, Maryland; letters from William Hand Browne (1828-1912), editor and librarian, describing his travels in the South during the early years of the Civil War; personal and family correspondence with friends and relatives, including letters from Senator Johnston containing references to his political activities; letters from the Sisters of the Order of the Visitation of Holy Mary concerning the education of the McMullen daughters at various schools run by the order; letters of Jean de Hedonville describing cattle ranching in Montana, life on the Crow Indian Reservation, and a camping trip to Yellowstone National Park; correspondence relating to the settlement of the estate of John Warfield Johnston; and business correspondence concerning his father's inventions and cattle raising.
Correspondence of the children of John Francis and Lavalette McMullen consists of letters of Mary McMullen, principally while a companion to Jane Agnes Riggs, daughter of George Washington Riggs, Washington banker, describing Riggs family history and their travels in Europe and the United States before World War I; letters to Mary from her cousin, novelist Mary Johnston (1870-1936); family letters of John Francis McMullen II (d. 1944), an engineer; letters of Benedict Dysart McMullen, writer, while serving with the American Red Cross in Europe during World War I; correspondence of Joseph Benjamin McMullen (d. 1965), inventor, concerning his many inventions, including aerial "drop" bombs during World War I, automobile accessories, kitchen utensils, household gadgets, and pressure and pull firing devices and collapsible vehicles during World War II; and papers relating to the settlement of a disputed legacy left Mary McMullen by Jane Riggs and correspondence concerning the sale of much of the inheritance. Also included are papers relating to the estates of the various members of the McMullen family; invention papers consisting of patents and descriptions of the work of John McMullen and Joseph B. McMullen; bills and receipts; lists of library books and Catholic publications purchased; manuscripts of William Hand Browne, John Bannister Tabb, Mary McMullen, and Dysart McMullen; and miscellaneous reports, certificates, and invitations from the many schools the McMullens attended.
Volumes consist of various business books of John McMullen and John Francis McMullen; subscription for the Catholic Church of Sinking Valley, 1830s; volumes of Joseph B. McMullen concerning his inventions; notebooks of writings and clippings of Mary McMullen and Dyeart McMullen; album of snapshots of their home, "Woodley," near Ellicott City, Maryland; and notebooks of Nicketti McMullen containing copies of old letters and data. There are also photographs of various members of the McMullen family and of homes at Wytheville, Thorn Springs, and Ellicott City.
Subject Headings
Browne, William Hand, 1828-1912; Johnston, Mary; McMullen, John Francis, 1830-1900; McMullen, Lavelette Johnson; McMullen, Mary, 1920-; Riggs family; Riggs, Jane Agnes; Tabb, John B. (John Banister), 1845-1909; Authors, American; Catholics -- United States; Inheritance and succession -- Washington (D.C.); Irish -- United States; Poets, American; Women authors, American; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Poetry
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1783-1963 and undated, (21 boxes)
  - 1783-1849 (Box 1)
  - 1850-1859 (Box 2)
  - 1860-1874 (Box 3)
  - 1875-1882 (Box 4)
  - 1883-1888 (Box 5)
  - 1889-1899 (Box 6)
  - 1900-1905 (Box 7)
  - 1906-1910 (Box 8)
  - 1911-1915 (Box 9)
  - 1916-1917 (Box 10)
  - 1918 (Box 11)
  - 1919-1920 (Box 12)
  - 1921-1922 (Box 13)
  - 1923-1925 (Box 14)
  - 1926-1929 (Box 15)
  - 1930-1933 (Box 16)
  - 1932-1935 (Box 17)
  - 1936-1939 (Box 18)
  - 1940-1944 (Box 19)
  - 1945-1954 (Box 20)
  - 1955-1963 and undated (Box 21)
- Legal Papers Series, 1780-1830s, (2 boxes) (Box 21)
  - 1780s-1830s (Box 22)
  - Peter and John McMullen (Box 22)
  - Joseph E. McMullen (Box 25)
  - Mary McMullen (Box 25)
  - Riggs Estate (Box 25)
- Pictures Series, (2 boxes) (Box 25)
  - Pictures (Box 23-24)
- Financial Papers Series, 1828-1949, (2 boxes) (Box 23-24)
  - 1828-1870s (Box 26)
  - 1880's-1949 (Riggs Family Inventory) (Box 27)
- Invention Papers Series, (2 boxes) (Box 27)
  - Joseph B. McMullen (Box 28)
  - John McMullen and Joseph B. McMullen (Box 29)
- Miscellaneous Series, (2 boxes) (Box 29)
  - Printed Material (Box 30)
    - Pamphlets (Box 30)
    - Leaflets (Box 30)
    - Clippings (Box 30)
  - Riggs Family Material (Box 30)
  - Writings and Poetry (Box 31)
    - John Bannister Tabb (Box 31)
    - Mary F. McMullen (Box 31)
    - Dysart McMullen (Box 31)
  - Miscellany (Box 31)
- Volumes Series, (3 boxes) (Box 31)
  - Volumes (Box 32-33)
  - Volumes, John and John Francis McMullen (Box 34)
- Oversize Materials (Box 34)
  - Two photographs of McMullen family and relatives at a reunion in Pennsylvania (Folder 1, Box 34)
  - Invention papers, John McMullen (Folder 2, Box 34)
  - Invention papers, John McMullen (Folder 3, Box 34)